so you have very, very uncertain data. So how can we detect and correct these inconsistencies? How can we represent that form of uncertainty? It's difficult. One thing you can do is document each step of the process, not only coding the historical information but what we call the meta-historical information, how is historical knowledge constructed, documenting each step. That will not guarantee that we actually converge toward a single story of Venice, but probably we can actually reconstruct a fully documented potential story of Venice. Maybe there's not a single map. Maybe there are several maps. The system should allow for that, because we have to deal with a new form of uncertainty, which is really new for this type of giant databases. And how should we communicate this new research to a large audience? Again, Venice is extraordinary for that. With the millions of visitors that come every year, it's actually one of the best places to try to invent the museum of the future. Imagine, horizontally you see the reconstructed map of a given year, and vertically, you see the document that served the reconstruction, paintings, for instance. Imagine an immersive system that permits to go and dive and reconstruct the Venice of a given year, some experience you could share within a group. On the contrary, imagine actually that you start from a document, a Venetian manuscript, and you show, actually, what you can construct out of it, how it is decoded, how the context of that document can be recreated. This is an image from an exhibit which is currently conducted in Geneva with that type of system. So to conclude, we can say that research in the humanities is about to undergo an evolution which is maybe similar to what happened to life sciences 30 years ago. It's really a question of scale. We see projects which are much beyond any single research team can do, and this is really new for the humanities, which very often take the habit of working in small groups or only with a couple of researchers. When you visit the Archivio di Stato, you feel this is beyond what any single team can do, and that should be a joint and common effort. So what we must do for this paradigm shift is actually foster a new generation of "digital humanists" that are going to be ready for this shift. I thank you very much. (Applause)
por eso tenemos datos muy, muy inciertos. Entonces, ¿cómo podemos detectar y corregir estas inconsistencias? ¿Cómo podemos representar esa incertidumbre? Es difícil. Algo que podemos hacer es documentar cada paso del proceso, no solo codificar la información histórica sino también lo que llamamos la información meta-histórica, cómo se construye el conocimiento histórico, documentar cada paso. Eso no garantizará la convergencia hacia una única historia de Venecia, pero probablemente podamos reconstruir una historia potencial de Venecia totalmente documentada. Tal vez no haya un solo mapa. Quizá haya varios mapas. El sistema debe permitir eso, porque tenemos que enfrentar una nueva forma de incertidumbre, algo nuevo para este tipo de gigantescas bases de datos. Y ¿cómo deberíamos comunicar esta nueva investigación a un público más amplio? Una vez más, Venecia es extraordinaria para eso. Con los millones de visitantes que recibe cada año es uno de los mejores lugares para tratar de inventar el museo del futuro. Imaginen que en el eje horizontal ven el mapa reconstruido de un año dado, y en el vertical, ven el documento usado para la reconstrucción, pinturas, por ejemplo. Imaginen un sistema inmersivo que permita meterse, bucear y reconstruir la Venecia de un año dado, una experiencia que podría compartirse en grupo. O al contrario, imaginen que parten de un documento, un manuscrito veneciano, y muestran lo que se puede construir a partir de eso, cómo se decodifica, cómo puede recrearse el contexto de ese documento. Esta es la imagen de una muestra que actualmente se lleva a cabo en Ginebra con ese tipo de sistema. Para concluir, podemos decir que la investigación en humanidades está a punto de experimentar una evolución quizá similar a lo ocurrido con las ciencias de la vida hace 30 años. Es realmente una cuestión de escala. Vemos proyectos que exceden lo que puede hacer un simple equipo de investigación y esto es realmente nuevo para las humanidades, que muy a menudo tienen el hábito de trabajar en pequeños grupos o solo con un par de investigadores. Cuando uno visita el Archivio di Stato siente que excede el trabajo de un solo equipo, y que debe ser un esfuerzo conjunto y mancomunado. Este cambio de paradigma requiere fomentar una nueva generación de "humanistas digitales" que estén preparados para el cambio. Muchas gracias. (Aplausos)